<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>blog on Yubari King&#39;s Blog</title>
        <link>https://yubariking.github.io/tags/blog/</link>
        <description>Recent content in blog on Yubari King&#39;s Blog</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>Ali Isa Talebi</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 20:17:59 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yubariking.github.io/tags/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Purpose of this blog</title>
        <link>https://yubariking.github.io/p/purpose-of-this-blog/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 20:17:59 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://yubariking.github.io/p/purpose-of-this-blog/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s worth explaining why I even have this blog and what motivates me to write here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two of my friends a while back started their own blogs, in which they post basically anything on their minds. I considered doing the same, but I thought I wanted my blog to be different. Not that I don&amp;rsquo;t think using a blog as a brain dump is bad, it&amp;rsquo;s just that I thought I could use it for a different purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figured what if I started to write about a specific topic I wish to become well-versed in. Being able to research a topic then condense it into a short blog post has many benefits. I am forced to read about a certain topic and gain a solid understanding of it so I can explain it. Then, by writing the concept in my own words, I reinforce my own understanding and also learn to articulate these concepts better. So, I thought why not supplement my learning in physics (which is what I&amp;rsquo;ll be studying in university) by creating this blog. And the best part is I can write about whatever I want. It serves as an outlet for me to explore niches in physics that catch my attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that means I am not intending to please an audience. I only work to please God anyways (sometimes this involves pleasing others). I will most likely share posts with friends and family and keep it at that. But the idea of random people reading these posts don&amp;rsquo;t bother me in the slightest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s about it. Of course I will occasionally throw in some random topics of my liking, but the goal is to consistently work on a physics post without worrying about how often I publish them (the topic dictates how long it takes to make a post). I will inshAllah keep myself in check, as I have already failed by posting once in February then taking a 3-month break. Discipline is a learned skill, and I have been diligently working on it. We shall see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, to anyone that reads these posts, I hope you find some benefit in them. If you ever wish to ask me any questions, I would be happy to answer them. You can check the contact page and send me an email.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
