<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>astronomy on Yubari King&#39;s Blog</title>
        <link>https://yubariking.github.io/tags/astronomy/</link>
        <description>Recent content in astronomy on Yubari King&#39;s Blog</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>Ali Isa Talebi</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 May 2024 20:21:51 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yubariking.github.io/tags/astronomy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Celestial Origin of Elements</title>
        <link>https://yubariking.github.io/p/celestial-origin-of-elements/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2024 20:21:51 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://yubariking.github.io/p/celestial-origin-of-elements/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;During the first few minutes of the Big Bang, the universe was rapidly expanding and thus cooling, allowing the protons and neutrons to bind together to form the first three elements (along with some of their isotopes) through nuclear fusion: hydrogen, helium and lithium. Today we find naturally occurring elements all the way up to Plutonium (94 on the periodic table). But how did all these 94 elements come into existence? Not all elements formed from the same process, as astronomers have identified multiple energetic mechanisms responsible for forging these elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;stellar-nucleosynthesis-from-helium-to-iron&#34;&gt;Stellar Nucleosynthesis: From Helium to Iron&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After cooling, the universe consisted of hydrogen and helium with small traces of lithium. After the universe was roughly 200 million years old, the first stars and galaxies began to form. Stars release energy and light because of the nuclear fusion taking place in their cores. They are characterized by their ability to create extreme pressures in their cores that facilitate temperatures of 4 million kelvin and above. These extreme temperatures cause atoms to collide at speeds that result in the fusion of elements that create a different element entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuclear Fusion within stars depends on how heavy they are (heavier stars have hotter cores and thus can fuse heavier elements). But this fusion stops at iron (more specifically Iron-56). Up until Iron-56, the nuclear fusion process always ended with less mass than with initial amount of mass that was used for nuclear fusion. This is why energy is released, because some of the mass got turned into energy (explained by E=mc^2). However, past Iron-56, fusing these elements is going to become energy inefficient for stars as the final result will need extra energy beyond the mass it started with. These energy requirements to form heavier elements are fulfilled even more energetic processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;supernovae-kilonovas-and-neutron-capture&#34;&gt;Supernovae, Kilonovas and Neutron Capture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a massive star is at the end of its life and has fused elements up to iron, its life ends by rapidly collapsing, causing a shockwave within the core when it can&amp;rsquo;t collapse further. The shockwave causes the star to explode outwards, leaving behind a black hole or a neutron star. This explosion heats matter to billions of degrees kelvin, causing atoms to fuse beyond iron. Another type of explosion known as a Kilonova is even more violent and occurs when two neutron stars collide, also causing nucleosynthesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another process that is responsible for creating new elements is neutron capture. Since neutrons have no charge, in a chaotic star neutrons can easily collide and merge into a nucleus. If there are too many neutrons relative to protons, the atom is becomes unstable and a process known as beta decay occurs. This process comes in two types, beta minus and beta plus, and in this case because the element is unstable, beta minus occurs in which neutrons transmute into protons, causing the element to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;closing-thoughts&#34;&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I mentioned the most common processes for nucleosynthesis, there are some other processes such as Cosmic Ray Spallation. However, their impacts are relatively minor compared to the other ones. Note that while the elements up to plutonium are naturally occurring, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean the &amp;ldquo;manmade&amp;rdquo; elements (elements heavier than Plutonium) are not synthesized in the universe. It is likely many of these are created but because of their short half-life they decay into lighter elements very fast and are thus left in nearly untraceable amounts which makes it unlikely for humans to find them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes after a unnecessary pause I have resumed posting, let&amp;rsquo;s see how far I make it this time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Olber&#39;s Paradox</title>
        <link>https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2024 11:59:20 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the 19th century, many scientists at the time posed a rather simple question: why is the night sky dark? While today this paradox can be answered with our updated model of the universe, scientists at the time lacked evidence and certainty to choose from their handful of possible solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, many scientists believed in a universe that&amp;rsquo;s static and infinite in space and time. This meant that there was an infinite amount of stars extending out forever. Because they assumed the universe to have an infinite age, that meant starlight regardless of their distance should be able to reach Earth. So Olber reasoned (although others before him addressed this problem too) that if there were infinite stars in our infinitely aged universe, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t the night sky be actually extremely bright?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply put, in an infinite universe, every line of sight should eventually hit some star light. And because there&amp;rsquo;s infinite time, our night sky should actually be lit ablaze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/olberparadox.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;505&#34;
	height=&#34;450&#34;
	srcset=&#34;https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/olberparadox_hue4fb0a15666bc1b6e7072670236b3deb_17421_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w, https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/olberparadox_hue4fb0a15666bc1b6e7072670236b3deb_17421_1024x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;Every line of sight from Earth meets a star&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;112&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;269px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today with our modern model for the universe, the solution for this Paradox can be answered with two reasons. First, we have proved our universe has a finite age (13.7 billion years) and had a beginning. This means that the light from distant stars have not reached Earth yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this means technically, given enough time our night sky should be bright when enough starlight reaches us. But this proves to be false, because we also have proved our universe is expanding which causes a redshift in light. The result is visible light shifts to longer wavelengths and thus makes it invisible to the naked eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/spectrum_2.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;690&#34;
	height=&#34;360&#34;
	srcset=&#34;https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/spectrum_2_hu119c08e9855d74d7175472df10b43872_45468_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w, https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/spectrum_2_hu119c08e9855d74d7175472df10b43872_45468_1024x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;Electromagnetic Spectrum&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;191&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;460px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
