<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Yubari King&#39;s Blog</title>
        <link>https://yubariking.github.io/</link>
        <description>Recent content on Yubari King&#39;s Blog</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>Ali Isa Talebi</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 16:50:58 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yubariking.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Radioactive Elements</title>
        <link>https://yubariking.github.io/p/radioactive-elements/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 16:50:58 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://yubariking.github.io/p/radioactive-elements/</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;radioactivity&#34;&gt;Radioactivity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes some atoms radioactive? An atom is radioactive when the nucleus is unstable. The stability of the nucleus is determined by two forces: the electrostatic force and the strong nuclear force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The electrostatic force is exchanged between charged particles, and since protons are the only charged particles in the nucleus they repel (like-charges repel). The strong nuclear force that works over very short distances (it&amp;rsquo;s effects are negligible with distances greater than a nucleus) is what counteracts the electrostatic force and thus what keeps the protons from flying apart. This force is acting to pull the nucleons together (protons and neutrons are collectively called nucleons) of the element.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in short, an element is radioactive when the electrostatic force and strong nuclear force aren&amp;rsquo;t in equilibrium. If they are, the element is considered stable. The neutron-to-proton ratio determines whether the element is stable or not. There are a few other factors that contribute to this stability such as binding energy, but for the most part this is how stability of an atom works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;radioactive-elements-on-the-periodic-table&#34;&gt;Radioactive Elements on the Periodic Table&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An element on the periodic table marked as radioactive indicates it&amp;rsquo;s most abundant isotope in nature is radioactive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means a radioactive element can have stable isotopes, they are just less abundant in nature. Conversely, a stable element can have radioactive isotopes (common example is Carbon-14) but its most common form is stable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the periodic table, most of the radioactive elements are heavier than Bismuth as the electrostatic force starts to dominate the strong nuclear force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://yubariking.github.io/p/radioactive-elements/table.png&#34;
	width=&#34;4634&#34;
	height=&#34;3250&#34;
	srcset=&#34;https://yubariking.github.io/p/radioactive-elements/table_hu6b7d8c0339a74ed93754663d4408bf76_417637_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w, https://yubariking.github.io/p/radioactive-elements/table_hu6b7d8c0339a74ed93754663d4408bf76_417637_1024x0_resize_box_3.png 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;Periodic Table showing the radioactive elements&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;142&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;342px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;types-of-radioactive-decay&#34;&gt;Types of Radioactive Decay&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When an atom is radioactive, it is going to undergo some form of decay to become stable. The different decay processes may involve the nucleus emitting or absorbing some particles to become more stable. In both cases, some radiation (emission of particles or waves) is released no matter what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all decay processes, the atom may either decay into a different isotope or transmute into a new element. There are two common types of radioactive decay, named after the first two letters of the greek alphabet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note the only reason these decay processes are named greek letters is because the scientists who discovered them didn&amp;rsquo;t know what type of radiation was being emitted. Otherwise, they probably would have been named something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;alpha-decay&#34;&gt;Alpha Decay&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In alpha decay, an unstable nucleus releases 2 protons and 2 neutrons, or essentially a helium-4 nucleus. It&amp;rsquo;s common for elements with an overpowering electrostatic force (mainly in heavier elements) to undergo alpha decay. Notice how releasing a helium-4 nucleus reduces the electrostatic force more than the strong nuclear force, allowing for the nucleus to stabilize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://yubariking.github.io/p/radioactive-elements/alphaDecay.png&#34;
	width=&#34;2878&#34;
	height=&#34;1618&#34;
	srcset=&#34;https://yubariking.github.io/p/radioactive-elements/alphaDecay_hu0a6f978fe1eed2e3ef7e0282b630e29b_92221_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w, https://yubariking.github.io/p/radioactive-elements/alphaDecay_hu0a6f978fe1eed2e3ef7e0282b630e29b_92221_1024x0_resize_box_3.png 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;Example of Alpha Decay&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;177&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;426px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;beta-decay&#34;&gt;Beta Decay&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two types of beta decay. Beta-minus decay is when a neutron converts into a proton, and thus emits a electron (beta particle) and an antineutrino. Beta-plus decay is when the opposite happens, a proton converts into a neutron, thus releasing a positron and neutrino. From these processes it&amp;rsquo;s possible for an element to transmute into a heavier or lighter element.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://yubariking.github.io/p/radioactive-elements/betaDecay3.png&#34;
	width=&#34;1275&#34;
	height=&#34;829&#34;
	srcset=&#34;https://yubariking.github.io/p/radioactive-elements/betaDecay3_hu98c2ac27e80561e6b8dbbbe9f3d7f315_363837_480x0_resize_box_3.png 480w, https://yubariking.github.io/p/radioactive-elements/betaDecay3_hu98c2ac27e80561e6b8dbbbe9f3d7f315_363837_1024x0_resize_box_3.png 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;Example of Beta Decay&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;153&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;369px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Purpose of this blog</title>
        <link>https://yubariking.github.io/p/purpose-of-this-blog/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2024 20:17:59 -0700</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://yubariking.github.io/p/purpose-of-this-blog/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s worth explaining why I even have this blog and what motivates me to write here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two of my friends a while back started their own blogs, in which they post basically anything on their minds. I considered doing the same, but I thought I wanted my blog to be different. Not that I don&amp;rsquo;t think using a blog as a brain dump is bad, it&amp;rsquo;s just that I thought I could use it for a different purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figured what if I started to write about a specific topic I wish to become well-versed in. Being able to research a topic then condense it into a short blog post has many benefits. I am forced to read about a certain topic and gain a solid understanding of it so I can explain it. Then, by writing the concept in my own words, I reinforce my own understanding and also learn to articulate these concepts better. So, I thought why not supplement my learning in physics (which is what I&amp;rsquo;ll be studying in university) by creating this blog. And the best part is I can write about whatever I want. It serves as an outlet for me to explore niches in physics that catch my attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that means I am not intending to please an audience. I only work to please God anyways (sometimes this involves pleasing others). I will most likely share posts with friends and family and keep it at that. But the idea of random people reading these posts don&amp;rsquo;t bother me in the slightest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s about it. Of course I will occasionally throw in some random topics of my liking, but the goal is to consistently work on a physics post without worrying about how often I publish them (the topic dictates how long it takes to make a post). I will inshAllah keep myself in check, as I have already failed by posting once in February then taking a 3-month break. Discipline is a learned skill, and I have been diligently working on it. We shall see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, to anyone that reads these posts, I hope you find some benefit in them. If you ever wish to ask me any questions, I would be happy to answer them. You can check the contact page and send me an email.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Celestial Origin of Elements</title>
        <link>https://yubariking.github.io/p/celestial-origin-of-elements/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2024 20:21:51 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://yubariking.github.io/p/celestial-origin-of-elements/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;During the first few minutes of the Big Bang, the universe was rapidly expanding and thus cooling, allowing the protons and neutrons to bind together to form the first three elements (along with some of their isotopes) through nuclear fusion: hydrogen, helium and lithium. Today we find naturally occurring elements all the way up to Plutonium (94 on the periodic table). But how did all these 94 elements come into existence? Not all elements formed from the same process, as astronomers have identified multiple energetic mechanisms responsible for forging these elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;stellar-nucleosynthesis-from-helium-to-iron&#34;&gt;Stellar Nucleosynthesis: From Helium to Iron&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After cooling, the universe consisted of hydrogen and helium with small traces of lithium. After the universe was roughly 200 million years old, the first stars and galaxies began to form. Stars release energy and light because of the nuclear fusion taking place in their cores. They are characterized by their ability to create extreme pressures in their cores that facilitate temperatures of 4 million kelvin and above. These extreme temperatures cause atoms to collide at speeds that result in the fusion of elements that create a different element entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuclear Fusion within stars depends on how heavy they are (heavier stars have hotter cores and thus can fuse heavier elements). But this fusion stops at iron (more specifically Iron-56). Up until Iron-56, the nuclear fusion process always ended with less mass than with initial amount of mass that was used for nuclear fusion. This is why energy is released, because some of the mass got turned into energy (explained by E=mc^2). However, past Iron-56, fusing these elements is going to become energy inefficient for stars as the final result will need extra energy beyond the mass it started with. These energy requirements to form heavier elements are fulfilled even more energetic processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;supernovae-kilonovas-and-neutron-capture&#34;&gt;Supernovae, Kilonovas and Neutron Capture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a massive star is at the end of its life and has fused elements up to iron, its life ends by rapidly collapsing, causing a shockwave within the core when it can&amp;rsquo;t collapse further. The shockwave causes the star to explode outwards, leaving behind a black hole or a neutron star. This explosion heats matter to billions of degrees kelvin, causing atoms to fuse beyond iron. Another type of explosion known as a Kilonova is even more violent and occurs when two neutron stars collide, also causing nucleosynthesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another process that is responsible for creating new elements is neutron capture. Since neutrons have no charge, in a chaotic star neutrons can easily collide and merge into a nucleus. If there are too many neutrons relative to protons, the atom is becomes unstable and a process known as beta decay occurs. This process comes in two types, beta minus and beta plus, and in this case because the element is unstable, beta minus occurs in which neutrons transmute into protons, causing the element to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;closing-thoughts&#34;&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I mentioned the most common processes for nucleosynthesis, there are some other processes such as Cosmic Ray Spallation. However, their impacts are relatively minor compared to the other ones. Note that while the elements up to plutonium are naturally occurring, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean the &amp;ldquo;manmade&amp;rdquo; elements (elements heavier than Plutonium) are not synthesized in the universe. It is likely many of these are created but because of their short half-life they decay into lighter elements very fast and are thus left in nearly untraceable amounts which makes it unlikely for humans to find them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes after a unnecessary pause I have resumed posting, let&amp;rsquo;s see how far I make it this time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Olber&#39;s Paradox</title>
        <link>https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2024 11:59:20 -0800</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In the 19th century, many scientists at the time posed a rather simple question: why is the night sky dark? While today this paradox can be answered with our updated model of the universe, scientists at the time lacked evidence and certainty to choose from their handful of possible solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, many scientists believed in a universe that&amp;rsquo;s static and infinite in space and time. This meant that there was an infinite amount of stars extending out forever. Because they assumed the universe to have an infinite age, that meant starlight regardless of their distance should be able to reach Earth. So Olber reasoned (although others before him addressed this problem too) that if there were infinite stars in our infinitely aged universe, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t the night sky be actually extremely bright?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply put, in an infinite universe, every line of sight should eventually hit some star light. And because there&amp;rsquo;s infinite time, our night sky should actually be lit ablaze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/olberparadox.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;505&#34;
	height=&#34;450&#34;
	srcset=&#34;https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/olberparadox_hue4fb0a15666bc1b6e7072670236b3deb_17421_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w, https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/olberparadox_hue4fb0a15666bc1b6e7072670236b3deb_17421_1024x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;Every line of sight from Earth meets a star&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;112&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;269px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today with our modern model for the universe, the solution for this Paradox can be answered with two reasons. First, we have proved our universe has a finite age (13.7 billion years) and had a beginning. This means that the light from distant stars have not reached Earth yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this means technically, given enough time our night sky should be bright when enough starlight reaches us. But this proves to be false, because we also have proved our universe is expanding which causes a redshift in light. The result is visible light shifts to longer wavelengths and thus makes it invisible to the naked eye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/spectrum_2.jpg&#34;
	width=&#34;690&#34;
	height=&#34;360&#34;
	srcset=&#34;https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/spectrum_2_hu119c08e9855d74d7175472df10b43872_45468_480x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 480w, https://yubariking.github.io/p/olbers-paradox/spectrum_2_hu119c08e9855d74d7175472df10b43872_45468_1024x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 1024w&#34;
	loading=&#34;lazy&#34;
	
		alt=&#34;Electromagnetic Spectrum&#34;
	
	
		class=&#34;gallery-image&#34; 
		data-flex-grow=&#34;191&#34;
		data-flex-basis=&#34;460px&#34;
	
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Archives</title>
        <link>https://yubariking.github.io/archives/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://yubariking.github.io/archives/</guid>
        <description></description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Contact</title>
        <link>https://yubariking.github.io/contact/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://yubariking.github.io/contact/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;mailto:isatalebi14@gmail.com&#34; &gt;isatalebi14@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Search</title>
        <link>https://yubariking.github.io/search/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://yubariking.github.io/search/</guid>
        <description></description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
